בוקר טוב Boker tov everybody, today's דף daf is מב mem bet
42. We pick up on מא עמוד ב mem aleph amud bet
at the two dots and we are where we are dealing right
now with the whole position of שמואל Shmuel that the גמרא Gemara
concluded that somebody who lends money with witnesses it does not have
to be repaid with witnesses. So if you're lending money be sure
to either get a שטר shtar or the second possibility is when
you're lending money you stipulate don't pay me back except with witnesses
and then it does have to be paid back with witnesses. But
the question is when you say don't pay me back except does
that just mean that witnesses have to be present or does that
mean that you have to be able to produce the witnesses to
prove that you've paid me back? So the question is are you
believed to say yes there were witnesses and they're no longer here
they're in מדינת הים medinat hayam they're off on some trip? So
which was שמואל's Shmuel position? So the conclusion of the גמרא Gemara
was not clear because there's a question what your גרסה girsa is
in the conclusion of the גמרא. Gemara. It's not clear whether we
פוסק pasken like שמואל Shmuel or not. Are you believed to say
yes there were witnesses and they're in מדינת הים medinat hayam or
no you have to actually produce the witnesses? So that remains a
little bit unclear in terms of the conclusion of the גמרא. Gemara.
So let's see how the גמרא Gemara continues because now we're going
to have a few interesting cases. So the first wide line actually
there's all these סימנים simanim these like ראשי תיבות rashei tevot to
understand to like you know mnemonic to know what's coming. But we'll
go to the third line after those ראשי תיבות. rashei tevot. ההוא
דאמר ליה לחבריה. Hahu d'amar lei l'chavrei. So now we're going to
have some cases. What's fun? Okay, application of some of the more
more theoretical discussion earlier. ההוא דאמר ליה לחבריה. Hahu d'amar lei l'chavrei.
Somebody said to his friend אל תפרעני כי פרטין פרע לי באפי
ראובן ושמעון. al tipraeni ki peratin pera'i li be'appei Reuven veShimon. When
you pay me back pay me back in front of ראובן Reuven
and שמעון. Shimon.
So it's sort of like only pay me back in front of
witnesses but he actually named who the two witnesses were. I want
to make sure that you pay me back in front of ראובן
Reuven and שמעון. Shimon. אזל ופרעיה באפי תרי מעלמא. azal upar'ei be'appei
terei me'alma. And of course this guy ignored him and paid him
back in front of two other witnesses. Now of course you know
it takes two to tango because the creditor accepted the money in
front of those other witnesses but all right anyway let's see what
happens. אמר אביי amar Abaye
and then basically he said to him right he said you know
so well I mean the question I guess is you know so
he said like you owe me the money maybe this was the
point that the you know the the debtor said I paid you
back in front of these other two people. He says you know
you borrowed a hundred dollars from me pay me back he said
I paid back in front of these other two people and the
way תוספות Tosafot understands it he said and of course this was
the classic case of and they went to מדינת הים. medinat hayam.
So I paid you back in front of לוי Levi and יהודה
Yehuda and they're no longer here they went to מדינת הים. medinat
hayam. And this guy said you know wait we stipulated and I'll
bring witnesses to the fact that we stipulated when I lent you
the money I said it would have to be in front of
ראובן Reuven and שמעון Shimon okay so and you're claiming that you
paid me back in front of לוי Levi and יהודה Yehuda and
they're no longer here. So אמר אביי. amar Abaye. So אביי Abaye
says באפי בי תרי אמר ליה באפי בי תרי פרעיה. be'appei bei
terei amar lei be'appei bei terei par'ei. He said pay back in
front of two. Why does it have to be specifically ראובן Reuven
and שמעון? Shimon? We don't take the stipulation of ראובן Reuven and
שמעון Shimon seriously. It's basically just you know any two witnesses are
considered as legitimate as any other two witnesses. So saying pay back
in front of ראובן Reuven and שמעון Shimon is a way of
saying pay me back in front of two witnesses and that's what
the guy did so he's believed. Again the way תוספות Tosafot reads
it is he said לוי Levi and יהודה Yehuda and they went
to מדינת הים medinat hayam and this is assuming like שמואל Shmuel
that that's sufficient. If you said I paid you back in front
of two witnesses and they went to מדינת הים medinat hayam you're
believed you don't have to actually produce the witnesses. So אביי Abaye
says the guy's believed. So אמר ליה רבא. amar lei Rava. So
רבא Rava said back no להכי אמר ליה באפי ראובן ושמעון. lehachi
amar lei be'appei Reuven veShimon. No if he only meant two he
would have said two. The reason he said ראובן Reuven and שמעון
Shimon is כי היכי דלא נדחייה ki heichi de-lo nitchayei so he
should not push him off so he shouldn't give one of these
שמואל Shmuel excuses. Oh yeah two witnesses it just happens to be
I'm mentioning לוי Levi and יהודה Yehuda because I happen to know
that they're on a you know on a six month trip to
China. Right? That's exactly what I was afraid of that you would
claim two witnesses and you'd claim that they're away somewhere. So that's
why I specifically said ראובן Reuven and שמעון Shimon so you could
not and I know ראובן Reuven and שמעון Shimon never go on
any trips and I know they'll always be around and I דווקא
davka did not want you to push me off. Okay. So here
the issue is the way תוספות Tosafot reads it it assumes like
שמואל Shmuel that if you say only pay me in front of
witnesses the guy would be believed to say right that he wouldn't
have to produce the witnesses. He'd be believed to say I paid
you in front of these witnesses and and they're not around. And
therefore says רבא Rava so if you specify which two witnesses it
has to be then that's specifically to close out that you know
that option of being able to make that claim. And that's why
yes when I say ראובן Reuven and שמעון Shimon you don't have
any more the option of any two witnesses. Specifically I'm saying ראובן
Reuven and שמעון Shimon in order so that you don't say some
two witnesses that are no longer here in order so
that. Now that's the way תוספות Tosfos reads it, that it's to
foreclose the option of the guy saying, oh yes, they were witnesses
who aren't here. Okay, what if however this guy said I paid
you in front of לוי ויהודה Levi u'Yehuda and here are לוי
ויהודה Levi u'Yehuda and let them come and testify to the fact.
And לוי ויהודה Levi u'Yehuda testified to the fact that I... I
keep on saying I, keep on switching from the מלווה malveh to
the לווה. loveh. Okay, David says, yes you know I know Dov
you said pay me in front of ראובן ושמעון Reuven v'Shimon but
I paid you in front of לוי ויהודה Levi u'Yehuda and here
they are and they're going to testify to the fact that I
paid you. And they testify to that fact. So according to תוספות,
Tosfos, okay, once you got witnesses even though you didn't do what
I stipulated, I said ראובן ושמעון, Reuven v'Shimon, okay, but at the
end of the day that doesn't matter, okay, that doesn't mean you
didn't pay me back my debt. You produced witnesses that said you
paid me back. End of story. Okay, so which makes a lot
of sense.
Wait, if this is a תנאי tnai for the... for the, you
know, loan then it shouldn't make a difference.
No, because at the end of the
day תנאי בגיטא אמר tnai b'gitta amar or whatever.
Alright, but that's a little, that's a little bit different. That's when
it's one-sided and you're doing some type of thing and you say
you only want it to take effect in the current circumstances. If
the actual story is that I lent David a hundred dollars and
he paid me back the hundred dollars, I don't have the right
to say you still owe me the money because of some crazy
condition that I make up. That's exactly what תוספות Tosfos says.
Okay, but you could refuse to accept it though, right?
I could always refuse... yeah, and that's an interesting question and then
could he throw it in my... in my property and whatever but
yes that's exactly תוספות's Tosfos's point. It's not like a תנאי tnai
by a גט get which is unilateral and I can say I
only want it to take effect under these circumstances. If he actually
returned the hundred dollars and he can prove it, then how can
I make some stipulation that says the debt isn't paid? That's exactly
תוספות's Tosfos's point. So if David were to produce לוי ויהודה Levi
u'Yehuda even if I said ראובן ושמעון, Reuven v'Shimon, תוספות Tosfos says
it doesn't matter what I said, he paid off the debt. Okay,
and that's why תוספות Tosfos says the specific case is he's not
producing the witnesses. He's trying to do a שבועה shvuah claim they're
in מדינת הים Medinas HaYam and I get to say you don't
get to claim that buddy. I said ראובן ושמעון Reuven v'Shimon so
that you could not claim מדינת הים, Medinas HaYam, you'd have to
produce ראובן ושמעון. Reuven v'Shimon. Okay, רש״י Rashi however disagrees. And from
רש״י Rashi it sounds like that if I said ראובן ושמעון, Reuven
v'Shimon, even if David produced לוי ויהודה, Levi u'Yehuda, I would be
entitled to say my stipulation meant that I get to invalidate all
other witnesses. That I get to claim that any other witness other
than ראובן ושמעון Reuven v'Shimon and the fact that you accepted the
money when I said ראובן ושמעון, Reuven v'Shimon, okay, you implicitly agreed
to the... the stipulation was that we are treating any other testimony
as invalid and the only testimony that would be accepted in court,
you implicitly agreed to that, that the only person's testimony that would
be accepted would be ראובן ושמעון. Reuven v'Shimon.
And by you accepting his payment though...
Yes... well no, then I'm saying I didn't accept your payment. You've
only proved I repaid based on לוי ויהודה. Levi u'Yehuda. We've agreed
that they're not believed. Okay, so if I admit I accepted the
repayment it's a different story but if all you have is לוי
ויהודה Levi u'Yehuda saying it, they're not acceptable witnesses. We agreed that
they wouldn't be acceptable witnesses.
So you have to basically say nothing about the repayment or...
or say that I wasn't repaid. Okay, so right now sort of
a very interesting debate and we're going to have a similar play
out in a minute, where I say only pay me back in
front of לוי ויהודה. Levi u'Yehuda. Okay, for תוספות Tosfos that can
mean that you don't get to get... make a claim that... excuse
me, only pay me back in front of ראובן ושמעון, Reuven v'Shimon,
it means you don't get to claim that there were two other
witnesses and they're in מדינת הים, Medinas HaYam, okay, that you actually
have to produce the witnesses. But for תוספות, Tosfos, if you produce
witnesses even if it's not what we stipulated, if the witnesses are
actually produced, I don't get to make some stipulation that invalidates those
witnesses. Whereas רש״י Rashi says no you actually do get to make
that. You're the guy lending the money, he's the guy accepting the
money, if he accepted the money on those terms, then there can
be terms that effectively invalidate all other witnesses. Okay, so that's an
interesting debate of רש״י ותוספות. Rashi v'Tosfos.
Any difference to the exclusion of...
Exactly, so now the
first case, say there's a dispute whether we repaid the money back,
is that why this is...
Yes, I'm saying you didn't pay me the money.
He said he paid him but that might be...
Well the point is that's the claim that he paid him or
whatever. According to רש״י Rashi it might actually be that he did
pay him and לוי ויהודה Levi u'Yehuda testified to that, but nevertheless
you get to dismiss them. Okay, so objectively we believe it was
paid because we believe לוי ויהודה, Levi u'Yehuda, but since you agreed
that their testimony is invalid, that's the way רש״י Rashi reads it,
then for הלכה halacha purposes it's effectively like you didn't repay it.
Okay, so that exactly is the question. Can you actually invalidate לוי
ויהודה? Levi u'Yehuda? That's the way רש״י Rashi reads it. Or can
no, and at most what I can do is I can say
you don't get to claim לוי ויהודה Levi u'Yehuda for off in
מדינת הים Medinas HaYam saw it. You have to actually produce witnesses.
Okay, yeah.
If לוי ויהודה Levi u'Yehuda are there, why don't we flip it
and then make the plaintiff take the שבועה? shvuah?
Oh, well again according
you mean according to רש״י's Rashi's approach. Because according to רש״י's Rashi's
approach it's like they're not there. You've basically invalidated them. You have
agreed, you the debtor has agreed to invalidate to testify on your
behalf anybody... since that was the stipulation I made and you accepted
the money on those terms,
the way
רש״י...
Rashi... It's not there from the, you know, formal court system, but
that would seem to
be—Oh, you mean why can't you just make like a שבועת היסת?
shvuat hesset? Why aren't they there enough to sort of satisfy the
שבועת היסת shvuat hesset requirement? Yeah, maybe you could make a שבועת
היסת. shvuat hesset. That's true. שבועת היסת shvuat hesset is always like
a good generic thing to demand. Okay, so now let's take a
look at the next case.
ההוא דאמר ליה לחבריה, Hahu de-amar lei le-havreih, once someone said to
his friend: כי פרעת לי, פרע לי באפי בי תרי דתנו הלכתא,
Ki parat li, pera li be-apei bei terei de-tanu hilchata, David, when
you pay me back, I want you to pay me back in
front of two witnesses that actually are like, you know, like a
little bit—they know תורה, Torah, they know הלכה. halacha. Okay, maybe I
was afraid that you know, if they were people that didn't know
הלכה, halacha, they wouldn't understand exactly the context of what they were
seeing. Okay, whatever it was, I made that stipulation. I want to
be paid back in front of two people that know
הלכה. halacha. אזל פרע ביני דיליה לדיליה. Azal pera beini dilei le-dilei.
Now David paid me back—forget, we're not even going to debate the
quality of the witnesses and whether they know הלכה—he halacha claims he
paid me back in private, okay? Or even maybe I even admit
to that—we're going to see I'm going to even admit to that.
אישתכחו הנהו זוזי. Ishtak-chu hanhu zuzei. So he paid me back in
private, which I admit to, and then what happened was some accident
happened with that money. Okay, there I was, I had the money
in my hand and somebody ran up and snatched it out of
my hand right as I turned away from David.
So, אישתכחו הנהו זוזי. Ishtak-chu hanhu zuzei. אתו לקמיה דרב נחמן. Atu
le-kamei de-Rav Nachman. We came to רב נחמן. Rav Nachman. אמר ליה,
Amar lei, so I said to רב נחמן: Rav Nachman: אין, כיבורי
קבלתינהו, In, kiburei kabaltinhu, yes, I concede that I took the money
from David מיניה, mineih, but because I said that it would have
to be in front of two people that knew הלכה halacha to
be a valid paying back, okay, when I actually took it, I
wasn't taking it as payment of the loan. Because remember, I stipulated
that the loan could only be repaid in front of two witnesses
that know הלכה. halacha. So in what capacity did I take it
back? דרך פיקדון. Derech pikadon. I was basically saying, David, you want
me to hold on to the hundred bucks? I'll hold on to
your hundred bucks. That's not paying up your hundred dollars you owe
me because we don't have two witnesses—well we'll get to that in
a minute—we don't have the two witnesses that I stipulated present. So
I'm just holding on to a hundred dollars for you. אמינא לאהדורי
גבאי פיקדון, Amina le-ahadurei gabai pikadon, I will have to keep this
money as a פיקדון pikadon עד דמשכחת בי תרי דתנו הלכתא, ad
de-mashkachat bei terei de-tanu hilchata, until there can be the two witnesses
that know הלכה, halacha, ומקיים תנאיין, u-mekayem tna'in, and then it will
be satisfying the conditions that I laid down for David. So since
I was just like a שומר חינם shomer chinam on that hundred
dollars—okay, it wasn't he paid up my debt yet, as far as
I'm saying it, I was just a שומר חינם shomer chinam and
then somebody came and snatched it out of my hands—so I'm exempt
from my חיוב שומרים chiyuv shomrim to pay back David. He hasn't
paid up his loan yet, he still owes me a hundred dollars.
That was my claim. אמר ליה, Amar lei, so רב נחמן Rav
Nachman said back to me: כיון דקמודית דודאי שקלתיה מיניה. Keivan de-ka
modit de-vadai shakaltih mineih. Look, you know, since you conceded that you
took the money from him, פירעון מעליא הוי. piraon malya hvei. Who
cares about any stipulation? He paid back the money.
אי אמרת לקיומי תנאיי, Ei amrat le-kiyumei tna'i, so you say, "Ah,
but wait, we stipulated that he's got to do it in front
of people that know
הלכה." halacha. זיל אייתינהו. Zil aitinhu. So go bring those witnesses, you
know, that are whatever, you know, that know הלכה. halacha. דהא אנא
ורב ששת דתנינא הלכתא וספרא וספרי ותוספתא וכולה גמרא. De-ha ana ve-Rav
Sheshet de-tanina hilchata ve-sifra ve-sifrei ve-tosefta ve-chula gemara. Hey, you know what?
You want some people who know הלכה? halacha? Take me and רב
ששת. Rav Sheshet. We know a lot of הלכה. halacha. We know
הלכה halacha and גמרא gemara and משנה mishna וכולה גמרא. ve-chula gemara.
Okay, and you know, we'll be here, we'll be able to sort
of, maybe give the money back to David and he'll give it
back to you in front of me and רב ששת Rav Sheshet
and יישר כוח, yashar koach, you can say you fulfilled your condition.
Now תוספות Tosafot says, if you look at a little תוספות, Tosafot,
תוספות Tosafot says בדיחותא בעלמא הוא דקמהדר ליה, bdichuta be'alma hu de-ka-mahadar
lei, ולא משום דצריך לקיום תנאו. ve-la mishum de-tzarich le-kiyumei tna'o. If
you really had to fulfill the stipulation, then you would say the
debt hasn't been paid yet, right? So he was really like joking
around with him. What he was really saying
was—Oh, that's a good point, רב ששת Rav Sheshet was blind.
Maybe you're right, maybe that's part of the joke. Anyway, so the
point is, and this gets back to the issue before: How much
can you as the מלוה malveh stipulate? Once you admit the debt
was paid up, you know, maybe before we debated whether you can
stipulate to invalidate witnesses, right? רש״י Rashi said you could invalidate the
witness, תוספות Tosafot said the stipulation was just saying that you'd have
to produce the witnesses, you couldn't say they're במדינת הים. be-medinat ha-yam.
You were saying they're paid—correct, you weren't saying you actually paid. All
right, so there there could be a question of to what degree
can the מלוה malveh stipulate about what's accepted as evidence against him?
Can you invalidate all other witnesses other than ראובן Reuven and שמעון?
Shimon? Can you exclude the claim of that they're במדינת הים? be-medinat
ha-yam? But here, you're admitting that you accepted the money, but what
you want to claim is that your stipulation— said that when that
money was paid, it wasn't being paid qua payment of debt. Okay?
And can you really stipulate that? The guy owes you a hundred
dollars, he gave you a hundred dollars. You get to stipulate that
it's not a payment of debt? So that's what the answer is:
no, I'm sorry, buddy. That you don't get to stipulate. He gave
you the hundred dollars, he owes you, you admit to that, the
debt is paid. And that's why it was a joke. Oh, you
said you needed people that know הלכה, Halakha, I'll bring רב ששת,
Rav Sheshet, we know a lot of הלכה, Halakha, but you can
maybe stipulate about the evidence. You can't stipulate that when he actually
gives you the money and you admit to that, that it's not
a payment of the debt. Now, there's an interesting רש"י. Rashi. רש"י
Rashi says, and this gets to Michael's point, רש"י Rashi says because
since you didn't say anything when David gave you that money back,
דברים שבלב אינם דברים. Devarim Shebelev Einam Devarim. Okay? You can't say
now, oh, I only meant it as a פיקדון pikadon not as
a payment of debt. But that sounds like if as David was
paying you the money, I was saying, David, I know you owe
me a hundred dollars and you're giving me a hundred dollars now,
but I am not accepting this hundred dollars as payment of the
debt. I'm only accepting it as a פיקדון, pikadon, you know, then,
then that actually would be able to frame it as a פיקדון.
pikadon. רבי עקיבא איגר Rabbi Akiva Eiger in the גיליון הש"ס Gilyon
Hashas disagrees. He says even if I say it explicitly, I don't
get the right to say that. Meaning if David says okay and
gives it to me as a פיקדון, pikadon, fine, then he's agreeing.
But if I'm saying I'm only accepting it as a פיקדון pikadon
and David is saying I'm giving it to you as a payment
of your debt, so he's saying it's a payment of my debt
and I'm saying it's a פיקדון pikadon and he hands it to
me, רבי עקיבא איגר Rabbi Akiva Eiger says it's a payment of
my debt. He owes me a hundred dollars, he gave me back
a hundred dollars, he said he was giving it to me as
a payment of my debt. I don't, even if I'm being explicit
about it, get to say that he didn't pay me back the
money. So that's also an interesting type of a question, okay? So
the first thing is you had a question where we agreed that
the מלווה malveh gets to stipulate to what constitutes evidence, where תוספות
Tosafot says I get to disqualify the claim that they're מדינת הים.
Medinat Hayam. רש"י Rashi says that the לווה loveh that I get
to even disqualify all other witnesses other than, you know, ראובן Reuven
and שמעון. Shimon. And here there's a question of does the מלווה
malveh get to stipulate when it's conceded that the money is paid,
whether it's considered a payment of the debt? And the answer is
no. But there is an interesting question of let's say the מלווה
malveh is being explicit, you know, and when the money is being
paid, and there רבי עקיבא איגר Rabbi Akiva Eiger says even that's
not going to help. If the לווה loveh paid you the money
and said he was paying it as a payment of the debt
and you admit to that, even if you're yelling and screaming and
saying you're not accepting it in that capacity, he paid you up
your debt, and I'm sorry, that's the end of the story. Yes,
Ben?
How about the opposite situation which actually happens a lot in contemporary
law where the לווה loveh says this is a פיקדון pikadon and
the מלווה malveh decides he wants it to be the payment for
the debt?
How does the מלווה malveh so?
So I have a mortgage with Chase bank but I also have
my paycheck direct deposited with Chase bank. It doesn't get credited to
the mortgage.
Oh, you don't get to take money from the לווה loveh who
doesn't want to give it to you. I mean the only way
you get to take money from the לווה loveh who doesn't want
to give it to you as a payment is if you go
to court and then the court actually, you know, seizes his property.
But you don't otherwise the reverse situation
is not an issue.
Right, exactly. You know, okay, so now let's take a look. So
that was two fun cases. Let's take a look as the גמרא
Gemara continues. Okay. So, okay. ההוא דאמר ליה לחבריה, Hahu d'amar lei
l'chavrei,
somebody said to his friend, הב לי מאה זוזי דאוזפתך, Hav li
mei'ah zuzei d'ozfitech, give me the hundred dollars that I lent you.
אמר ליה, Amar lei, לא היו דברים מעולם, Lo hayu devarim me'olam,
I have no idea what the heck you're talking about, nothing like
this ever occurred. אזל אייתי סהדי דאוזפי ופרע, Azal ayiti sahedi d'ofsei
u'farei,
then David, after saying, David, I'm sorry you're going to be the
bad guy here, after claiming that nothing like this ever happened, okay,
he then brought witnesses that actually said he did borrow the money
and he paid it back.
אמר אביי, Amar Abaye, מאי נעביד, mai ne'avid,
what should we do? Meaning how can we make David pay? אינהו
אמרי אוזפי ואינהו אמרי פרעי, Inhu amri ofsei v'inhu amri parei, they
said he borrowed, they said he paid. So there's if you go
without the witnesses, so that's a כופר הכל kofer hakol and he
gets off the hook. Maybe has to make a שבועה. shvu'ah. Okay.
If you go with the witnesses, they said he borrowed, they said
he paid. Either way, we consider it like he paid. That's what
אביי Abaye said. That's pretty reasonable.
רבא אמר, Rava amar, כל האומר לא לויתי כאומר לא פרעתי דמי.
kol ha'omer lo laviti, k'omer lo parati dami. No, when David said
לא היו דברים מעולם, Lo hayu devarim me'olam, nothing like this ever
happened, he is implicitly testifying that he never paid up a debt.
He's saying he never borrowed, but he's also saying he never paid.
Okay. So therefore what we do, this is very fascinating according to
רבא. Rava. The witnesses that you brought, David, testify you did borrow
the money. Yes, they testify you paid it, but you yourself have
testified you didn't pay. Let's say David explicitly said, let's say David
brought witnesses that said David borrowed a hundred dollars from Dov and
paid him up. And then David says, I am actually testifying that
I did not pay Dov back the money. Then we would say
your own personal testimony against yourself trumps the testimony of the witnesses.
Why? Why? Two is like a hundred. I understand, but the principle
is הודאת בעל דין כמאה עדים דמי. hoda'at ba'al din k'mei'ah edim
dami. You're believed against yourself even more than witnesses.
No, but two is like a hundred.
I understand, but the principle is יותר ממאה עדים, yoser mimei'ah edim,
okay? That's the principle.
Your testimony against yourself beats, you can always obligate yourself against witnesses.
So if David explicitly said... Yes if Dave, if David says look,
I know I never paid you. I don't remember if I borrowed
the money. They're saying I borrowed the money and they're saying I
paid you, but no, I am saying I never paid you, then
of course you'd have to pay. Okay, if he explicitly said he
never paid. So what Rava is saying is, even though he didn't
explicitly say he didn't pay, he implicitly said it. By saying לא
היו דברים מעולם, lo hayu devarim me'olam, he is telling us that
he never paid back the money. And therefore that implicit testimony trumps
the testimony of witnesses that said he did pay it. Okay, that's
pretty harsh.
Isn't that sort of like believing half their testimony?
I mean, well, we're not believing half.
They say they borrowed...
Right, we're believing half of each person's testimony. Yeah, it's a little
harsh according to Rava. I would say also that Tosafot points out
that if David said I didn't borrow rather than saying לא היו
דברים מעולם, lo hayu devarim me'olam, then we would have interpreted I
didn't borrow to mean I don't still owe him the money. Okay,
so like let's say David said another example, no way, no way,
right? So oh, well no way maybe means not that he didn't
borrow,
maybe it just means that he borrowed and he paid, right? But
he says לא היו דברים מעולם, lo hayu devarim me'olam, so says
that's a phrase that we can't reinterpret. That's a phrase that cannot
mean I borrowed and I paid back, and therefore implicitly he's saying
that he didn't pay back, and we combine that testimony with the
testimony of the witnesses that said that he borrowed. That's at least
Rava's position. Right, even though the witnesses say he did pay back,
exactly. It's pretty harsh. That's Rava's position. Okay,
exactly. הוא דאמר ליה לחבריה, Hu de'amar leh lechavereh, somebody said to
his friend, הב לי מאה זוזי דמסקת בי, Hav li me'ah zuzei
demaskat bi, give me the hundred dollars that I have that you
owe me. Although this is phrased in the, I don't know what
the English term for this would be, meaning how would you say
it from the perspective of the creditor, that I have
outstanding with you, right?
That is outstanding with you, I
guess you could say outstanding against you.
Okay, anyway, okay, give me the hundred dollars that you owe me.
אמר ליה לא פרעתי לך באפי פלוני ופלוני? Amar leh lo parati
lach be'afey ploni u-ploni? So David says what are you talking about,
Dov? What do you mean that I still owe you? Didn't I
pay you back in front of פלוני ופלוני? Ploni u-Ploni? אתו פלוני
ופלוני ואמרו לא היו דברים מעולם. Atu ploni u-ploni ve'amru lo hayu
devarim me'olam. So Ploni and Ploni come, let's bring Ploni and Ploni.
Ploni and Ploni said no, he never paid you back.
All right, so now, but they don't know anything about him borrowing.
They don't know anything about him borrowing. So now do we just
sort of go back to square one and say, so I claim
he borrowed, he said he didn't, he's a כופר הכל, kofer hakol,
and he's actually, he doesn't pay, maybe he has to make a
שבועת היסת? shevuat hesset? Or do we say the fact that he
said he paid in front of Ploni and Ploni and Ploni and
Ploni said he didn't, means that his claim now, we don't go
back to square one. Now when he says he paid, you know,
now when he says he paid me back, his whole his credibility
has been undermined, right? Do you understand that? Based on the fact
that he claimed Ploni and Ploni, and Ploni and Ploni contradicted him?
So okay, so רב ששת, Rav Sheshet, סבר רב ששת למימר הוחזק
כפרן. Savar Rav Sheshet lemeimar huchzak kafan. So
Rav Sheshet said okay, if David had just said I paid you
back, he would have been believed, maybe with a שבועת היסת. shevuat
hesset. Now that this whole thing has happened, his credibility has been
undermined and he's no longer believed to say that he paid me
back. And as Rashi says, even if David were ready to take
a שבועה, shevua, we wouldn't believe him anymore. His credibility has been
undermined and he has to pay me back. הוחזק כפרן. huchzak kafan.
In this particular case. In this particular case, it doesn't mean forever.
Next, a month from now, I say I lent him a hundred
dollars again, he would be believed. Right, it's not like his general
status is he's no longer believed in court. But in this case,
thank you for clarifying, in this case his credibility is undermined. That's
a very reasonable position. אמר ליה רבא, Amar leh Rava, Rava said
back to this, כל מילתא דלא רמיא עליה דאינשי לאו אדעתיה. Kol
milta dalo ramyah aleh de'inshi la'av adaiteh. No, it doesn't undermine his
credibility. Things that people don't pay close attention to, you know, that's
not sort of seen as their responsibility, they're not paying close attention.
Now of course, yes, exactly. If somebody, if I have to, if
David has to pay me back a hundred dollars, okay, even if
he didn't designate Ploni and Ploni, even if Ploni and Ploni happened
to be on the street, and he's the debtor and he knows
he owes me the money, and in the back of his mind
he might know that he might have to prove it someday in
court, presumably it is רמיא אדעתיה, ramya adaiteh, right? He said Rava
says כל מילתא דלא רמיא עליה דאינשי, kol milta dalo ramyah aleh
de'inshi, something that's not somebody's responsibility, but this is David's responsibility to
pay back that money and he knows he might have to prove
it in court, so presumably he is paying attention to whether Ploni
and Ploni are there. So that is definitely the חידוש chiddush of
Rava. Rava's חידוש chiddush is that, you know, maybe because David knows
that the general הלכה halacha is that he's believed to say that
he paid me back. The general הלכה halacha is that David, right,
this is what we've been saying, a person doesn't have to produce
witnesses. A person can say I paid you back as long as
there's no שטר, shtar, he'd be believed, maybe David would be prepared
to take a שבועה. shevua. So Rava's חידוש chiddush is since David
doesn't need the witnesses, since he's believed to say he paid me
back, maybe with a, maybe he would have to take a שבועה,
shevua, then he's not paying that close attention to who are those
two guys standing there that happen to be witnessing. He thinks they're
פלוני ופלוני, Ploni ve-Ploni, but he doesn't bother to go over to
them and get exactly their names and clarify that because at the
back of his head he knows I don't really need witnesses. Okay,
so that's why
it's
לא רמיא עליה. lo ramyah aleh. didn't need the witnesses. And because
of that, when it's not ראובן ושמעון, Reuven v'Shimon, it doesn't undermine
his credibility. All right. Next case. ההוא דאמר ליה לחבריה, Hahu de'amar
lei lechavrei, somebody said to his friend, "Hab li sheish mei zuzi
d'masikna becha," David, give me the 600 זוזי zuzi that I lent
you. אמר ליה, Amar lei, "V'lo particha mei kavei aftzi?"
I don't understand, don't you admit that I gave you back 100
what? No, don't you admit that I did—Michael's going to fill in
the blank—don't you admit that I gave you back 100, you know,
I don't know, what? Gallnuts, that's right, 100 units, 100 pints of
gallnuts, and דקיימי בשישה שישה, d'kaimi b'shisha shisha, and every pint of
gallnuts was worth six dollars? So I paid you back in gallnuts,
okay? I paid you back 600 dollars worth of gallnuts. אמר ליה,
Amar lei, "Lav b'arba arba havu kaimi?"
What do you mean? They weren't going at six dollars a pint,
they were going at four dollars a pint. You only paid me
back
400, you still owe me 200. אתו תרי סהדי, Atu trei sahadei,
and then actually אתו תרי סהדי, atu trei sahadei, and ואמרי אין
בארבעה ארבעה הוו קיימי, v'amri in b'arba arba havu kaimi, and then
I brought two witnesses who testified that at that day—we all agreed
what the day was that David paid me back, okay, maybe they
didn't—and they all agree that at that day the market price for
gallnuts was four dollars a pint at that day, okay? So אמר
רבא הוחזק כפרן. Amar Rava huchzak kafan. So now David is a
הוחזק, huchzak, is, is his credibility has been undermined. Okay, now the
point is like, I don't know, you know, if David made me
backtrack and said, okay fine, they were worth four but I paid
you the other 200 in cash, okay, I paid you 100 gallnuts
that were worth 400 dollars and the other 200 in cash, or
whatever David is now going to say, he's no longer believed. Normally
again, that would be a כופר הכל kofer hakol and he wouldn't
be believed? He said he paid me up the full debt. But
now that he was proven lying about the, about the price of
the gallnuts, he's no longer—he lost credibility in this case. So אמר
רמי בר חמא הא מילתא קול מילתא דלא רמיא ליה דאינשי לאו
אדעתיה, Amar Rami bar Chama ha miltha kol miltha d'lo ramye lei
d'inshi lav adaitei,
didn't you say that something that's not somebody's responsibility to know, they're,
you know, they're not paying close attention to and that doesn't undermine
their credibility when they get it wrong? אמר ליה רבא קצוצה דתרא
מידכר דכירי אינשי. Amar lei Rava kitzutza d'tara midkar dicheeri inshi.
No, the price of something, you know, the קצוצה kitzutza means like
the cut value of the שער. sha'ar. You know, you even say
that in, in modern Hebrew now, right? Like when you say "what's
the rate for the dollar," מה השער, mah hashaar, okay? Because, you
know, because transactions would happen in the city gate, okay? So that's
why the gate, whatever, the שער sha'ar means to represent like the
rate of exchange. So the specific rate of exchange people pay attention
to. It doesn't mean I always know exactly how much apples cost,
but if David is paying me back in gallnuts, he knows how
much the gallnuts are worth per pint, okay? So therefore that is
considered to be a conscious lie. He didn't forget that he thought
the gallnuts were worth six and they were really worth four. That
is considered to be a conscious lie because he obviously would have
known that if he was paying me back in gallnuts. And therefore
it undermines his credibility and he's not believed to say he paid
me the other 200 in cash. Okay. ההוא דאמר ליה לחבריה, Hahu
de'amar lei lechavrei, somebody said to his friend—these are fun, these cases,
aren't they? They actually certainly, you know, make it much more graphic,
much more, you know, concrete. ההוא דאמר ליה לחבריה, Hahu de'amar lei
lechavrei, somebody said to his
friend, "Hab li mei zuzi demasikna becha," David, give me the hundred
dollars that I lent you. והא שטרא, Veha shtara, here's a שטר.
shtar. אמר ליה, Amar lei, it's, you know, this time I'm not
going to let you come and say that there were witnesses and
one witness and—I got a שטר, shtar, I got a document. אמר
ליה, Amar lei, "Particha," David says, "I paid up the שטר." shtar.
Okay, yeah, you didn't give me back, I lost my receipt, but
I'm claiming I paid you back. Now obviously that would normally be
rejected. But I actually אמר ליה, amar lei, so I actually concede
that David paid me the 100 dollars. But I say, "הני סטראי
נינהו," Hani sitrayeninu, yes, you know what David, it's true, you did
give me 100 dollars yesterday. But when you gave me that 100
dollars, that was for some other debt you owed me. That was
not for the debt represented by this
שטר. shtar. Actually there's one debt that we had בעל פה be'al
peh for 100 dollars and that was what the 100 dollars was
that you paid me—I admit you paid 100 yesterday—that was for that
other debt, but the שטר shtar debt, that's still outstanding. Okay, so
that's very interesting. Once I admit that there was 100 paid and
I can't prove that this other loan existed, I just claim the
other loan existed, has the fact that I admitted 100 dollars without
any evidence of any other loan mean that I now actually have
undermined the שטר shtar and can and can no longer collect from
David? So let's take a look. So אמר רב נחמן, Amar Rav
Nachman, איתרע שטרא. itra shtara. Yes, your שטר shtar has been undermined.
Okay, now what does it mean that your שטר shtar has been
undermined? So רש"י Rashi says you can't collect with it at all
anymore. You admit that a hundred dollars was paid, you can't prove
that that was for some other debt, you can't prove that there
was another debt. So we're going to assume that that hundred dollars
was a payment of the שטר shtar and you can't use it
at all. תוספות Tosafot quotes רבינו תם Rabbeinu Tam who says, yeah,
but at the end of the day you still have a שטר,
shtar, and the your holding of a שטר shtar without the guy's
receipt still is prima facie evidence that you're owed the money. So
רבינו תם Rabbeinu Tam says you now have to take a שבועה.
shvuah. That is now if I want to collect with this שטר
shtar after admitting that a hundred dollars was paid, but I claim
it was for something else, I can use the שטר shtar if
I'm prepared to make a שבועה shvuah that it hasn't been paid.
Okay, so there's an interesting debate. I mean תוספות Tosafot has both
opinions, but between רש"י Rashi and רבינו תם, Rabbeinu Tam, whether this
completely makes the שטר shtar unusable or whether now if I want
to use the שטר shtar I have to make a שבועה shvuah
to back it up. Okay, so let's take a look. Anyway, so
רב נחמן Rav Nachman says my admission that I got a hundred
dollars even though I claim it was for something else undermines the
שטר. shtar. רב פפא אמר לא איתרע שטרא. Rav Pappa amar lo
itra shtara. You didn't undermine the שטר. shtar. You're still holding on
to the שטר. shtar. That's still prima facie evidence you haven't been
paid. David didn't prove he gave you a hundred dollars. If David
proved he gave me a hundred dollars, end of story. I admit
that I got the hundred dollars, but I'm claiming it was for
some other debt.
Okay, so that's what רב פפא Rav Pappa says. לא איתרע שטרא.
lo itra shtara. ורב פפא מאי שנא מהא דאמר ליה לחבריה? V'Rav
Pappa mai shna me'ha d'amar lei lechavrei? So according to רב פפא,
Rav Pappa, the שטר shtar is still valid. How is that different
than the case of somebody said to his friend, הב לי מאה
זוזי דמסיקנא בך? Hav li me'ah zuzei d'massiqna bach? So now it's
a different case. I say to Charlie, Charlie, give me the hundred
dollars that I lent you. והא שטרא. V'ha shtara. Here's the שטר.
shtar. ואמר ליה לאו אטורי יהבתיה ניהלך ואתית וספייתא אמכסא? V'amar lei
lav atury yhavtie nihlach v'atit v'sipyeita amchasa? So Charlie says, Dove, you
lent me that hundred dollars so that I should invest it in
some business of buying and selling cattle for you.
Okay, and then basically you lent me the hundred dollars and then
I would whatever pay it back and I would keep the profits
or whatever I'd invest it, whatever the case is.
ואתית וספייתא אמכסא. v'atit v'sipyeita amchasa. You came to me at the
cattle market and I paid you back
the
hundred dollars, and you accepted it. אמר ליה הנהו סטראי נינהו. Amar
lei hanu sitrai ninhu. Yes, it's true you gave me a hundred
dollars at the cattle market, but that was for some other debt.
Okay, now here the difference is, and which the גמרא's Gemara going
to say, is that we all agree that the hundred dollars that's
represented by the שטר shtar was for investment in cattle. That we
agree, that that was that hundred dollars. And we all agree that
he paid me a hundred dollars at the cattle market. But I'm
claiming, oh, that was for some other debt. Okay, so the circumstances
that the money was lent for cattle investment and the paying back
was at the cattle market makes it that much harder for me
to claim that that was for some different debt. Okay. ואמר
ליה הנהו סטראי נינהו, v'amar lei hanu sitrai ninhu, ואמר רב פפא
איתרע שטרא. v'amar Rav Pappa itra shtara. It's undermined. So if there
it's undermined, why not here? So the גמרא Gemara says no, התם
כיון דאמר אטורי יהבתיה ניהלך, hatam kivan d'amar aturi yhavtie nihlach, since
it's conceded that the money was given to invest in cattle, ומיטורי
שקלתיה, umituri shakaltie, and then you were paid back at the cattle
market after maybe I sold some cattle, and you concede all of
that, איתרע שטרא. itra shtara. That undermines the שטר shtar then. We're
going to not believe a claim that that was for some other
debt. Okay, that's that case. הכא הנהו סטראי נינהו, hacha hanu sitrai
ninhu, but in this case, right, you admit you got a hundred
dollars, but there was no other context, so you're believed to say
that hundred dollars was for something else. Okay, so מאי הוי עלה?
mai havi ala? What was the conclusion when the guy has the
שטר shtar but admits he got money but claims it was for
something else? רב פפי אמר לא איתרע שטרא. Rav Papi amar lo
itra shtara. רב שישא בריה דרב אידי אמר איתרע שטרא. Rav Sheisha
brei d'Rav Idi amar itra shtara. So the debate continued.
Okay, so רב פפי, Rav Papi, excuse me, says the same thing
as רב פפא, Rav Pappa, לא איתרע שטרא, lo itra shtara, and
רב שישא Rav Sheisha says the same thing as רב נחמן Rav
Nachman and he says איתרע שטרא, itra shtara, it's undermined. והלכתא איתרע
שטרא. V'hilchta itra shtara. And the הלכה halacha is, Mike isn't here
because Mike always wants to know what the הלכה halacha is, and
the גמרא Gemara concludes: once you admit that you got a hundred
dollars, even though you're holding a שטר, shtar, you are no longer
believed to say, then that undermines the שטר. shtar. You're not believed
to say it was for something else. And now again, רש"י Rashi
says it means you can't use the שטר shtar at all. תוספות
Tosafot says it means you might have to take a שבועה shvuah
if you want to use the שטר. shtar. Okay, so now the
גמרא Gemara says like this, okay. והני מילי דפרעיה באפי סהדי ולא
אדכר ליה שטרא. V'hani mili d'parie b'apei sahadi v'lo adchar lei shtara.
Now all of this is, is if the hundred dollars was paid
up, actually I said, and I spoke too soon, I forgot this
line of the גמרא. Gemara. I said the case was was that
I admitted to the hundred dollars. Okay, here the גמרא Gemara is
saying that there actually were witnesses. Okay, to the hundred dollars. There
were witnesses to the hundred dollars which makes it I guess even
a bigger חידוש chiddush of the position that says that you're believed
to say
הנהו סטראי נינהו. hanu sitrai ninhu. Okay. So it's not even my
own admission, but I still am claiming that was for something else.
So that's a bigger חידוש chiddush of the position that says לא
איתרע שטרא, lo itra shtar, that even with witnesses that he paid
me, I can make a claim that that was for some other
debt. Okay, you understand that? On the one hand, what do you
mean, he's got witnesses. On the other hand, I've got a שטר.
shtar. My holding of the שטר shtar means he hasn't paid me.
All right, so that becomes very interesting. Witnesses that money was given,
a שטר shtar that's effectively a testimony that it hasn't been paid.
So that's the position that says even with witnesses, לא איתרע שטרא.
lo itra shtar. That's a bigger חידוש chiddush than I was saying
before. Okay, but now the גמרא Gemara clarifies. והני מילי, V'hani milei,
this issue of איתרע שטרא itra shtar is or the debate of
איתרע itra or לא איתרע, lo itra, even though we פוסקין pasken
that it is, that it is איתרע, itra, is דפרעיה באפי סהדי
ולא איתרע ליה שטרא. d'pari b'apei sahadi v'lo itra lei shtar. That
David brings the witnesses that he paid me the money, but they
didn't mention, there was no mention of the שטר. shtar. David didn't
say, "Okay, Dov, give me the שטר." shtar. Okay, because obviously if
he had said that, they would then implicitly the witnesses would be
directly testifying that it was payment of that debt.
Okay. אבל פרעיה בין דידי לדידי, Aval pari bein didai l'didai, now,
so I, again, I apologize, I, this is the case, but if
it's a case where there are no witnesses, and I admit that
it was paid and I say that it was paid for some
other purpose, so in that case, מיגו דיכול למימר לא היו דברים
מעולם יכול נמי למימר סטראי נינהו. migo d'yachol l'meimar lo haya devarim
me'olam, yachol nami l'meimar sitrai ninhu. That case actually I would be
believed. Okay, so there's three scenarios. One scenario is David says he
paid me and he brings witnesses and the witnesses actually say that
David asked for the שטר shtar back. So that case, obviously the
witnesses are testifying that it's payment of the debt. Scenario number two
is David brings witnesses that money he gave me a hundred dollars,
but there was no discussion of context. And that's the question. According
to one opinion, that completely is proof that he paid off my
שטר, shtar, איתרע שטרא. itra shtar. Okay. And the other opinion is
no, there's witnesses he gave me a hundred dollars, but my holding
of the שטר shtar still evidence that he owes me that debt,
and I get to claim that that hundred dollars was something else,
even in the presence of witnesses. That's scenario number two where we
debate it. But scenario number three is I say I admit that
David gave me the hundred dollars and say it was for something
else, but there's no evidence of that. I admit to it. And
there the גמרא's Gemara saying everybody agrees the שטר shtar is still
valid. Because since I could just as not admitted. David says, "Dov,
don't you admit that I gave you a hundred dollars yesterday?" and
I could say no. So since if I wanted to lie I
could have just denied that he gave me the money yesterday, so
when I admit that he gave me the money and said that
it was not for payment of debt, it was for something else,
not for this שטר, shtar, then I am believed. Okay. So everybody
got that? Three cases. Okay. So וכדאבימי בריה דרבי אבהו, u'khd'Abimi brei
d'Rabbi Abbahu, like Abimi the son of Rabbi Abbahu, which was some
case in כתובות Ksuvos which was exactly this case. So if
I, so if there's no evidence that David gave me the money
and I admit that he did and says it was for another
purpose, that's the same as just denying that he paid me the
money, and therefore I am believed. Okay. ההוא דאמר ליה לחבריה, Hahu
d'amar lei l'chavrei, now somebody said to his friend. מהימנת לי כל
אימת דאמרת לי לא פרענא. Mehemnat li kol eimat d'amart li lo
parana. So David said to me,
similar to the discussion before about invalidating other witnesses or whatever that
debate of Rashi and Tosafot. David says to me, "I, Dov, I
will accept this hundred dollars and I know you're afraid that you
might not get that money back or like whatever, I'll tell you
what Dov, any time I am going to say right now in
front of these witnesses or write it down or whatever, that you,
Dov, will always be believed to say that I haven't paid off
the debt." Okay, and that's what he's doing because maybe he needs
to say that in order for me to lend him the money
because I'm afraid that he might try to get out of it
and claim other witnesses or whatever. He says, "Dov, here's the condition.
You are always believed to say that the debt has not been
paid up." Okay. כל אימת דאמרת לא פרענא, Kol eimat d'amart lo
parana, you will be believed as two witnesses.
אזל פרעיה באפי סהדי, Azal pari b'apei sahadi, and then David paid
up in front of witnesses. And I said, "You didn't pay up."
Okay, and he has witnesses that he
did. Abaye and Rava דאמרי תרווייהו, d'amri tavai, הא הימניה, ha hemnai,
David said that he would believe me, that means even more weighty
than the testimony of witnesses.
מתקיף לה רב פפא, Matki lah Rav Pappa, Rav Pappa challenges this.
נהי דהימניה טפי מנפשיה, Nee d'hemnai tfei m'nafshei, no, when David says
he believes me, it means "Dov, I'll believe you over any claim
I make to the
contrary." Okay. נהי דהימניה טפי מנפשיה Nee d'hemnai tfei m'nafshei means that
I'd be believed against David, so he doesn't get to be a
כופר הכל kofer hakol and just walk out with some שבועת היסת.
shvuas hesset. Okay, that's what he meant. טפי מסהדי מי הימניה, Tfei
misahadi mi hemnai, he never implied by saying "I'll believe you" that
you get to beat out witnesses. Okay, so now of course that
leads to the next point of the גמרא, Gemara, let's say he
did say that explicitly. הוא דאמר ליה לחבריה מהימנת לי כבי תרי.
hu
d'amar
lei l'chaveirei mehemanas li k'bei trei. So now David said to me,
Dov, you'll be believed to me as weighty as witnesses. Okay, כל
אימת דאמרת לא פרענא, kol eimat de'amrat lo parana, anytime you say
that you haven't paid. אזל פרעיה באפי תלתא, azal perei bapei tlata,
and now David paid me in front of three witnesses.
So now he believed me like two, so it's two against three,
so do we like neutralize each other and therefore, you know, he's
still believed to say that and therefore it's like he didn't pay,
or do three beat out two? Wait a minute. אמר רב פפא,
amar Rav Pappa, כבי תרי הימניה כבי תלתא לא הימניה. k'bei trei
hemneih k'bei tlata lo hemneih. No, he only said I'll believe you
as two, he didn't say I'll believe you as three. Three still
beats out two. אמר ליה רב הונא בריה דרב יהושע לרב פפא,
amlei Rav Huna brei d'Rav Yehoshua l'Rav Pappa, so רב הונא Rav
Huna said to רב פפא, Rav Pappa, אימת דאמרי רבנן דאזלינן בתר
רוב דעות? eimat d'amrei Rabbanan d'azlinan batar rov de'ot? When do Rabbis
say that two versus three that the number makes a difference? Three
is better than two. הני מילי באומדנא. hanei milei b'umdana. That's like
if we're trying to do an assessment of how much a property
is worth, we're seizing somebody's property in payment of debt, you bring
in different assessors to assess the value, you go by the majority,
and therefore, three is better beats out two. דכמה דנפישי בקיאי טפי,
de'kama dinfishi beki'ei tfei, the more people there are, the more we
assume that they know what they're talking about, which isn't always true,
you know, but okay fine. אבל לענין עדות, aval l'inyan eidus, but
when it comes to testimony, מי איכא תרי כמיאה ומאה כתרי, mei'ika
trei k'mei'a u'mei'a k'trei, so in court here we're dealing with testifying.
So if David gave me weight as two witnesses, weight of two
witnesses is the same as weight of... I beat out three witnesses
or at least I neutralize the three witnesses. Okay, לישנא אחרינא, lishana
achrina, another version of this discussion. הוא דאמר ליה לחבריה מהימנת לי
כבי תרי. hu d'amar lei l'chaveirei mehemanas li k'bei trei. You're believed
to me like two. כל אימת דאמרת לא פרענא, kol eimat de'amrat
lo parana, as whenever you say that I didn't pay. אזל ופרעיה
באפי תלתא. azal u'parei bapei tlata. He paid me in front of
three. אמר רב פפא, amar Rav Pappa, כבי תרי הימניה כבי תלתא
לא הימניה. k'bei trei hemneih k'bei tlata lo hemneih. Same initial position.
It's only two, it's not three, I don't neutralize. מתקיף לה רב
הונא בריה דרב יהושע, maskif lah Rav Huna brei d'Rav Yehoshua, תרי
כמיאה ומאה כתרי. trei k'mei'a u'mei'a k'trei. No, two's as good as
a hundred and I do neutralize. But now here's the new point.
ואמר ליה, ve'amar lei, כבי תלתא. k'bei tlata. Let's say David says
to me, Dov, I'll believe you as weighty as three witnesses. Now,
why did he have to say three? Once you say two, it
means as witnesses. So once he is saying three, ואזל ופרעיה באפי
ארבעה, ve'azal u'parei bapei arba, and then David paid me in front
of four witnesses, then I do lose out. If he had said
two, I would have neutralized the four. But if he says three,
I don't neutralize the four. Why? 'Cause once he's saying three, he's
no longer saying that it's just about the weight quality as a
witness. It's actually a question of number as well. כיון דנחית לדעות
נחית לדעות. keivan de'neichis l'de'ot neichis l'de'ot. Since he mentioned three, three
is no better than two. The only value of mentioning three is
to say it's not just going to be about counting as a
witness, it's going to be about how many you are. Right? 'Cause
that's the only difference between three and two is not that they're
better as witnesses, they're just more of them. So once David's saying
the numbers matter, okay, then four actually will beat me out. Now
this idea that you can actually give somebody believability against witnesses, I
should mention is very relevant in עגונה agunah cases or some solutions
of an עגונה. agunah. Because one of the solutions, for example, of
an עגונה agunah is that, you know, we make a קידושין על
תנאי. kiddushin al tnai. That's one of the suggestions that have been
put out there. Okay, but what happens if we make a קידושין
על תנאי kiddushin al tnai and then the husband has the right
according to the גמרא Gemara to be מבטל mevatel the תנאי tnai
anytime during the marriage. So let's say, you know, it's a קידושין
על תנאי kiddushin al tnai and the guy isn't giving the גט
get and then the woman says, fine, but based on our stipulation,
the whole קידושין kiddushin was on תנאי tnai and therefore the whole
קידושין kiddushin is nullified. And the husband says, yeah, I was מבטל
mevatel that תנאי, tnai, that תנאי tnai is no longer in effect.
Okay, and here are even witnesses. I went to ראובן ושמעון Reuven
and Shimon and said to them I מבטל mevatel the תנאי. tnai.
Okay, so what we put in, I mean Michael Broyde who has
done this, you know, in his whole sort of trying to come
up with putting together all the different, I mean it's not only
him, this was precedes him, put together all the different solutions for
the עגונה, agunah, so when this is done it says here's the
תנאי tnai and the husband says I believe my wife as you
know equal to witnesses, actually I think we might say equal to
a hundred witnesses, you know, to be believed against me and any
witnesses I bring to say that I was מבטל mevatel the תנאי.
tnai. So, you know, so that's actually the way, you know, you
foreclose the ability to do certain things. So, you know, and anyway,
so that's like this type of a device is actually, you know,
important to foreclose certain abilities.
Does that actually have to be in the כתובה ketubah or does
it?
No, that's like it's a separate thing. Yeah, okay. All right, moving
on. אין נשבע, ein nishba, now we finally, so that was the
end of all those fascinating cases. Now we get next in the
משנה. Mishnah. I need to show you something very interesting in רש"י.
Rashi. If you look at רש"י, Rashi, רש"י Rashi says,
if you look at רש"י, Rashi, רש"י Rashi is about near the
end of the ב"ח bach on the right hand column, like if
look in the ב"ח, bach, if you go to רש"י, Rashi, you
see where there are these like little quote marks in the רש"י,
Rashi, like these five words with these quote marks in them. Anyway,
רש"י Rashi says there, שכחתי מלפרש המשנה והנני מפרש כאן. shachachti milifaresh
hamishnah vehineni mefaresh kan.
Do you see that? That's pretty amazing. רש"י Rashi says I forgot
to actually explain the משנה mishnah back when the משנה mishnah was
quoted, let me explain the משנה mishnah here. Which I find is
totally bizarre because we're always hearing about how רש"י Rashi had multiple
editions of his work. Why didn't he just go back in his
next later edition and put this, you know, maybe this was his
last, I don't know, anyway it's very strange. But anyway, back to
the גמרא. Gemara. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says אין נשבעין על
טענת חרש שוטה וקטן ואין משביעין את הקטן. ein nishba'in al ta'anat
cheireish shoteh vekatan ve'ein mashbi'in et hakatan.
If a if a חרש שוטה וקטן cheireish shoteh vekatan says they
gave me money and I say, yes, you gave me a hundred
dollars and I paid back fifty or whatever, then because I'm responding
to a חרש שוטה וקטן, cheireish shoteh vekatan, I don't have to
take a שבועת מודה במקצת. shevuat modeh bemiktzat. And similarly, if a
קטן katan borrowed money from me, okay, he would not have to
take a שבועה. shevuah. All right now, so all of that is
very interesting because you also wonder, like, if a קטן katan does
he appear in court, does he have a representative, how does the
whole thing work? Okay, but anyway the אין נשבעין על טענת חרש
שוטה וקטן, ein nishba'in al ta'anat cheireish shoteh vekatan,
let's take a look. מאי טעמא? mai ta'ama? What's the reason? אמר
קרא כי יתן איש אל רעהו כסף או כלים. amar kra ki
yitein ish el re'ehu kesef o keilim. If a man gives his
neighbor כסף או כלים kesef o keilim לשמור ואין נתינת קטן כלום.
lishmor ve'ein netinat katan klum. The act of giving is not meaningful
in this context. Now, that doesn't really mean it like it doesn't
mean like if he gives me the money I don't owe him
the money, like if a קטן, katan, a קטן katan could have
property and he could lend me money and he could create a
debt. So what it really means is is that it's somehow it's
not איש, ish, it's not כי יתן איש, ki yitein ish, and
somehow this strange idea, somehow even though it's like there is that
debt, it doesn't satisfy the criteria here, and the fact that I
got it from him as a קטן katan means it can never
translate into making a שבועה shevuah about it. And let's keep on
reading as the גמרא Gemara continues. אבל נשבעין לקטן ולהקדש. aval nishba'in
lekatan ulehakdeish. But you will take an oath to a קטן katan
or to a הקדש. hakdeish. So the גמרא Gemara says, one minute.
והאמרת רישא שאין נשבעין על טענת חרש שוטה וקטן. veha'amarta reisha she'ein
nishba'in al ta'anat cheireish shoteh vekatan. But you just said you don't
take an oath to a חרש שוטה וקטן. cheireish shoteh vekatan. So
what does it mean you swear to a קטן? katan? So אמר
רב ביבי בטענת
אביו. amar Rav Bibi beta'anat aviv. So actually this is where it
matters. He says, here's the case.
The קטן katan comes to me and says, my father lent you
a hundred dollars, okay, and I say, yes, but I paid back
fifty. So in this case, it is the I am swearing to
the קטן, katan, but it's based on a debt that I owed
the father. So since the way we excluded it above was because
it wasn't כי יתן איש, ki yitein ish, it was the question
of the initial transaction. Was the initial transaction money I got from
an adult or money I got from a minor? So what he
is saying now is if I admit, if the if the money
I got was from an adult, but now the minor is taking
me to court, I actually would have to take a שבועה shevuah
to him. So it's not so much about swearing to the קטן
katan and the קטן katan is now demanding the money in court.
It's really all the question of whether I got the money from
the adult or from the minor, which is funny, like why that
should matter. Okay, anyway, so that's what he says. בבא בטענת אביו.
beba beta'anat aviv. רבי אליעזר בן יעקב היא. Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov
hi. And this is רבי אליעזר בן יעקב. Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov.
דתניא דתניא בברייתא. detanya detanya bevraita. רבי אליעזר בן יעקב אומר פעמים
שאדם נשבע על טענת עצמו. Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov omer pe'amim she'adam
nishba al ta'anat atzmo. Sometimes you will have to take an an
oath based on your own claim against yourself, meaning that there's not
really another side that's making the claim against you. כיצד? keitzad? What's
an example? אמר לו מנה לאביך בידי והאכלתיו פרס. amar lo maneh
la'avicha beyadi vehe'echaltiv pras. I go over to this kid and I
say, you know what, I borrowed a hundred dollars from your father
and and excuse me, מנה לאביך, maneh la'avicha, yeah, and I paid
back fifty dollars of it. Okay,
so that's like a מודה במקצת, modeh bemiktzat, but nobody's demanding the
money from me. I'm telling it to this minor, to this orphan
who inherited his father's estate and I'm going up and telling him
I borrowed a hundred dollars from your father and paid back fifty.
So רבי אליעזר בן יעקב Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov says הרי זה
נשבע. harei zeh nishba. I have to take an oath even though
there's no real claim against me. זהו שנשבע על טענת עצמו. zehu
shenishba al ta'anat atzmo. That's somebody swearing making an oath based on
their own claim against themselves. Now, that would seem a little bit
absurd if like ממש mamash I just went and told the guy
I owed him fifty dollars. So what the גמרא Gemara seems to
read it is, well, maybe there's a קטן katan involved and the
קטן katan is saying to me that I owe me the money
that that I owe the money. Okay, but that still normally we
would not give weight to a טענה ta'ana of a קטן, katan,
to a claim made against me by a קטן. katan. But in
this case we will. So if you piece that together what it
means is
the money was from the father so it wasn't כי יתן איש.
ki yitein ish.
The money was received from an adult. The קטן katan is challenge
is demanding it from me, that hasn't been said, we're going to
read that into it, and I admit to half. So that's a
case of נשבעין על טענת קטן. nishba'in al ta'anat katan. But because
at the end of the day it's a קטן katan demanding the
money, to some degree it's being framed as טענת עצמו ta'anat atzmo
because it's really not a side that has standing in court. Okay,
וחכמים אומרים אינו אלא כמשיב אבידה פטור. veChachamim omrim eino ela kemeshiv
aveidah patur. Yeah, come on, you're just like you know returning a
lost object. Otherwise this guy wouldn't know about it at all or
you know and therefore you're just a nice guy. We're not going
to make you obviously take a שבועה. shevuah. ורבי אליעזר בן יעקב
לית ליה משיב אבידה פטור? veRabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov leit lei meshiv
aveidah patur? So now do I jumped ahead to the answer because
if the case was really I just came and admitted it and
nobody made a claim against me, everybody should admit I'm like just
returning a lost object. I could have just stayed at home and
not said anything. right? So how could I now make a שבועה
shvua that I'm being a nice guy and telling him that I
owe him fifty dollars? So אמר
רב בטענו קטן. Amar Rav beta'ano katan. So he wasn't talking literally
I just was admitted it all on my own. But the other
side wasn't a weighty side. The other side was the minor was
making that demand from me, okay? And Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov says
presumably that's enough of a טענה, ta'ana, enough of a demand, since
I got the money from the father and I have to make
a שבועה מודה במקצת shvua modeh be-miktzat and that would be the
case in our משנה. Mishnah. And the חכמים chachamim say no, you're
still משיב אבידה. meshiv aveida. Nobody is holding you back, you could
have still just denied it since it's just a קטן. katan. You
wouldn't have been embarrassed to deny it to the קטן. katan. You
wouldn't have with you know refrained from doing that. Okay, so now
the גמרא Gemara says קטן, katan, one minute, so אמרת אין נשבעין
על טענת חרש שוטה וקטן. amarta ein nishba'in al ta'anat cheresh shoteh
ve-katan. So now we seem to have an answer to the משנה.
Mishnah. You're not נשבע nishba on טענת חרש שוטה וקטן ta'anat cheresh
shoteh ve-katan when they gave you the money, but when you got
the money from the father, you would swear on טענת חרש שוטה
וקטן. ta'anat cheresh shoteh ve-katan. That actually was exactly how we were
trying to reconcile the two lines in the משנה. Mishnah. But the
גמרא Gemara pushes back, the גמרא Gemara thinks no, that still is
טענת קטן, ta'anat katan, that can't be what the משנה Mishnah is
talking about. So fine, לעולם גדול. le-olam gadol. Fine, it's not the
טענה ta'ana of a קטן. katan. The orphan is an adult.
ואמאי קרי ליה קטן? ve-amai kari leh katan? לגבי מילי דאבוה קטן
הוא, legabei milei de-avuhi katan hu, because vis-à-vis the father he's a
minor, meaning he's not the person that directly lent the money. So
now what we're saying is when the משנה Mishnah says that I
have to swear to a קטן, katan, what it really means is,
first it says I don't swear to a קטן, katan, then it
says I do. So when it says I do, it doesn't really
mean a קטן. katan. What it really means is I will swear
to an orphan who's coming with me, an adult orphan who's coming
to me with a claim of a debt that I owe the
father, okay? So now the גמרא Gemara says one minute, but if
it's an adult,
then why would the חכמים chachamim say you're משיב אבידה? meshiv aveida?
And why would Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov or whoever it is say
that it's טענת עצמו? ta'anat atzmo? It's a real adult making a
claim against me. So אי הכי ei hachi says the גמרא, Gemara,
I'll just read one more line, טענת עצמו? ta'anat atzmo? What do
you mean טענת עצמו? ta'anat atzmo? טענת אחרים הוא. ta'anat acherim hu.
It's other people making the claim, it's an adult making the claim.
טענת אחרים והודאת עצמו. ta'anat acherim ve-hoda'at atzmo. Fine, other people make
the claim but you admit it. So the גמרא Gemara says כולהו
נמי טענת אחרים והודאת עצמו נינהו. kulu'hu nami ta'anat acherim ve-hoda'at atzmo
ninhu. Every case of מודה במקצת modeh be-miktzat is somebody makes a
claim and I admit it. Why are we calling this that I'm
only making the claim against myself? So do we have to, can
we give one more minute? Let's start, okay. אלא בדרבה קמיפלגי. Ela
bi-de-Rabbah kamiflagi. Here's the issue. דהאמר רבה, De-amar Rabbah, here's the whole
reason of מודה במקצת. modeh be-miktzat. מפני מה אמרה תורה מודה במקצת
הטענה ישבע? Mipnei mah amrah Torah modeh be-miktzat ha-ta'ana yishava? Why does
the guy who admits to part take an oath? Meaning why can't
you, and the way the תוספות Tosafot says this, why do I
have to take an oath if I admit to half? I could
have just denied everything and gone off scot-free. So just believe me
that I'm saying half because I could have said nothing. No, because
of the following. חזקה אין אדם מעיז פניו בפני בעל חובו. Chazakah
ein adam me'iz panav bifnei ba'al chovo. You would not have had
the חוצפה chutzpah to deny everything to this guy who lent you
the money. והאי בכוליה בעי דליכפריה, ve-hai be-kulei bei de-lichpariah, you really
would have wanted to deny everything because you're already, maybe you are
lying and you would have really wanted to deny everything. והאי דלא
כפריה משום דאינו מעיז פניו בפני בעל חובו, ve-hai de-lo kafreih mishum
de-eino me'iz panav bifnei ba'al chovo, but you just couldn't do that,
you couldn't have that much חוצפה. chutzpah. Okay? And therefore you can't
say I could have just claimed that I don't owe anything and
walked off. No, that much חוצפה chutzpah you don't have. ובכוליה בעי
דלודיה ליה, u-ve-kulei bei de-lodei leh, so then if you don't have
חוצפה, chutzpah, why not just you really felt you should admit it
all or you were ashamed, you wouldn't have the חוצפה chutzpah to
do it, so at some level you would have admitted it all.
והאי דלא אודיה ליה אשתמוטי הוא דקא משתמיט מיניה. ve-hai de-lo odei
leh ishtamutei hu de-ka mishtamit mineih. You're just trying to buy time.
סבר עד דהוו לי זוזי ופרענא ליה, Savar ad de-havei li zuzei
u-farana leh, that I'll get the money and I'll pay him up,
meaning if we thought that you were a real גנב ganav maybe
a שבועה shvua wouldn't help. But you're not a real גנב. ganav.
You're just trying to postpone it. ורחמנא אמר רמי
שבועה עילויה כי היכי דלודיה ליה. ve-Rachmana amar rami shvua ileih ki
heichi de-lodei leh. So put a שבועה shvua in order to admit.
So you can't say believe me I could have denied it all
because you wouldn't have had the חוצפה chutzpah to deny it all.
That's the basic point. So now בכולהי. be-kulei. רבי אליעזר בן יעקב
סבר לא שנא בבו ולא שנא בנו אינו מעיז. Rabbi Eliezer ben
Yaakov savar lo shena bo ve-lo shena bno eino me'iz. You would
not have had the חוצפה chutzpah to deny it even to the
son. And therefore you don't have a מיגו migo that you could
have denied it, and you still have to take a שבועה shvua
even to the son. והלכך לאו משיב אבידה הוא, ve-hilkach lav meshiv
aveida hu, you're not a משיב אבידה. meshiv aveida. ורבנן סברי בבו
הוא דאינו מעיז. ve-Rabbanan savri be-vo hu de-eino me'iz. No, you wouldn't
have the חוצפה chutzpah to deny it to the guy who gave
you the money. אבל בפני בנו מעיז. aval bifnei bno me'iz. If
I was lying, if I wanted to lie, I would have had
no problem lying to the son. I wouldn't have lied to the
father, but I would have no problem lying to the son. ומדלא
מעיז, u-mi-de-lo me'iz, and since I didn't say I owe you nothing,
I actually said to this adult son I owe you fifty, משיב
אבידה הוא. meshiv aveida hu. Okay, then actually you should believe me.
So here the debate is what we have said now is that
the case is we're not dealing with a קטן, katan, we're dealing
with an adult who's coming with a claim of the father. That's
the case in the משנה Mishnah where you're taking a שבועה shvua
to a קטן, katan, not really a קטן. katan. And the issue
is a debate in that case, should I be believed? Because I
could say yes, I'm a מודה במקצת, modeh be-miktzat, but since you're
just the son, had I wanted to lie I would have denied
it. And the issue is it's a debate in that case, should
I be believed because I could say, yes, I'm a מודה במקצת,
modeh bemiktzat, but since you're just the son, had I wanted to
lie I would have denied it all. Okay, and that's the debate
of whether in that case I have to make a שבועה shvua
or not. Okay.